Finding Aid for Alumni Association (University of Michigan) records, 1845-2001
Bentley Historical Library
Alumni Association (University of Michigan) records
1845-2001
Bentley Historical Library
University of Michigan. Alumni Association.
8730; Bimu; H1a; 2
169.8 linear feet (in 171 boxes)
1 oversize volume
84.4 GB (online)
The Alumni Association of the University of Michigan was established in 1897 following a consolidation of the Society of Alumni with the alumni societies of the professional schools. The Michigan Alumnus became the association's official organ. As the organization grew, local chapters were established and provided greater structure. The records include files pertaining to the Alumni Association's administrative office and various chapters and interests groups. This includes national and international U-M alumni and alumnae clubs, the Alumnae Council, the Society of Alumni, the University of Michigan Black Alumni (UMBA-formerly the African American Alumni Council (AAC)), and the Reunion of Black Graduates (RBG). The records include but are not limited to correspondence, minutes, reports, and survey responses, audiovisual materials, digital files, photographs, and publications.
The records are open for research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated computers.
The records were transferred from the Alumni Association (donor 1617 ) in a number of accessions beginning in 1945. The photographs were transferred in 1975. The most recent accessions were received in 2017.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
The collection is arranged into 14 series: 1. Administrative Files; 2. Alumnae Council Files; 3. Alumni Club Files; 4. Alumni Societies; 5. Classes and Reunions; 6. Class Officer and District Files; 7. Class Reunion Files; 8. Scrapbooks, Registers and Accounts; 9. Society of Alumni; 10. Special Projects and Topics; 11. Topical Files; 12. Audio-Visual Materials; 13. Photographs; 14. Publications.
Alumni Association
Alumni activities at the University of Michigan began almost as soon as there were alumni. The Society of Alumni was formed in 1845, immediately after the first commencement. At first the society accepted graduates of any college as members, but by 1853 it had defined itself as the alumni organization of the University of Michigan, and specifically of the Literary College. The society combined social activity with promotion of the interests of the University in its early years, but was not particularly important to the running of the University. In 1874, however, the society began to take a more active role, establishing the Williams professorship fund, which was used for the support of retired professors.
In the 1870s alumni of the professional schools began to organize their own societies, law alumni in 1871, the Association of Medical Alumni in 1875, and dentistry, pharmacy, and homeopathic medicine alumni by 1884. After a financial scandal in the Society of Alumni came to light in 1889, a movement began to consolidate all the alumni societies, in order to improve confidence in the organizations. In 1897 the societies were combined into the Alumni Association.
The new society soon began to expand its activities. It bought the Michigan Alumnus, a private publication founded in 1894, to serve as its official organ. The number of local alumni clubs was expanded and an endowment fund was established to support the association's activities.
Although the University began to support the Alumni Association financially during Shirley W. Smith's tenure as secretary of the association (1901-1904), the University's support of the association increased greatly with the appointment of Harry Burns Hutchins to the presidency of the University in 1910. Hutchins saw the association as a potentially important source of funds for the University. The Association's ties with the University's development activities became even stronger after World War II, when the Phoenix Project, the $55 Million campaign, and other campaigns relied heavily on alumni support.
In 1923 the structure of the association was changed, with the local alumni chapters becoming the basic units of the organization. At this time a field secretary was also appointed, to stimulate the development of the local chapters and organization of districts.
By the end of the 20th century the Alumni Association boasted more than 104,000 members. The mission statement described the association as "an independent worldwide organization that nurtures lifelong relationships with and among current and future Michigan alumni. As a committed partner of the University, the Association offers programs of relevance and service to alumni and creates support for the University. Underlying all that we do is the belief in the value of education to the well-being of society, and a commitment to integrity, diversity, and service." Activities include organizing alumni excursions and lecture tours, coordinating reunions, operating a career assistance network, and offering lifelong learning opportunities.
The Alumnae Council
Until 1914, when an alumnae representative was added to the board of directors of the Alumni Association, alumnae were not organized at the university level. A number of alumnae clubs had been organized in various localities, but there was no central organization. In 1917 a Central Coordinating Committee was formed as a part of the Alumni Association, to allow alumnae to support the needs of women students. At that time, the University was the first co-educational institution to be represented at an Alumnae Conference held in Washington, D.C. Prior to the establishment of the university organization, however, University of Michigan alumnae took an active role in the building of the national Association of Collegiate Alumnae, now referred to as the American Association of University Women. Alice Freeman Palmer, President of Wellesley College, (1876, Ph.D. hon, 1882) was one of three University of Michigan women who established the Association in 1882 in conjunction with women from the University of Wisconsin, Oberlin College, Boston University, Cornell, Vassar, Smith, and Wellesley.
The original University of Michigan organization functioned as a central correspondence committee whose purpose was to keep in touch with the needs and life of women at the university and report activities to the alumnae. In the first year, there were 14 alumnae groups in various cities throughout the United States. The first meeting of all University of Michigan alumnae was held in 1917 in Ann Arbor to discuss projects for the organization to undertake that were important to the University's women. From that meeting came the plans to fund and construct Alumnae House, the first women's residence.
In 1920, the central correspondence committee changed its name to the Alumnae Council of the Alumni Association to better reflect the growing function of the committee as an integral part of the Alumni Association. It was also decided to admit representatives from each of the alumnae groups to the Council. In 1921 a constitution for the organization was adopted. It was also in 1921 that the Council began a campaign to raise $1,000,000 for a women's building to meet the social as well as the educational requirements for women on campus. By 1926, the money was raised and in 1928 the cornerstone was laid for the Michigan League building.
In 1930, the Council began a program in cooperation with the Graduate School to aid women with financial needs. The first graduate endowment fund established was the Lucy Elliot Fellowship. This was soon followed by the Alice Crocker Lloyd Fellowship. The Henderson House, a women's cooperative dormitory, was also established, with residence based on scholastic achievement. The Council continues to sponsor scholarships for women in addition to other fellowships and loans.
The Council's activities remained somewhat independent of those of the Alumni Association until 1955, when an attempt was made to integrate alumnae activities into those of the Association.
University of Michigan Black Alumni (UMBA)
Established in 1976, and under the guise of its former title (the African American Alumni Council (AAAC)), the UMBA was created with the purpose of addressing issues, providing support, and enhancing the educational experience and performance of African American faculty, staff, and students of the University of Michigan. The Council also serves to increase the involvement of African American alumni in University of Michigan programs, activities, and events. In 1994, the African American Alumni Council was formally incorporated as an affiliate member of the University of Michigan's Alumni Association. In conjunction with the Alumni Association, the Council sponsors several key events, programs and awards including the Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Symposium and Scholarship, the Dr. Leonard F. Sain Award, the Annual Reunion of Black Graduates, the Camp Michigania retreat, as well as numerous programs, including the Minority Recruitment program.
Current information is available at the Alumni Association's web site at the following URL: https://alumni.umich.edu/
General Secretaries and Executive Directors of the Alumni Association
1897 Louis P. Jocelyn (Acting Secretary)
1897 Ralph C. McAllaster
1898-1901 James H. Prentiss
1901-1904 Shirley W. Smith
1904-1929 Wilfred B. Shaw
1929-1958 T. Hawley Tapping
1958-1962 John E. Tirrell
1962-1966 Robert O. Morgan
1966-1994 Robert G. Forman
1994- Steve Grafton
The collection spans 1845-2001. The textual records of the Alumni Association (boxes 1-133) are largely unprocessed, and are described in only general terms in this finding aid. Exceptions include files maintained by Marjorie Williams who served as the vice chair and chair of the Alumnae Council from 1960 to 1962, Class Reunion files, and Topical Files.
Additions to the collection (boxes 168-171) incorporate records, audiovisual materials, photographs, and publications pertaining to the University of Michigan Black Alumni (UMBA). To note are materials specifically related to the African American Alumni Council (AAAC)-formerly the UMBA, and the Reunion of Black Graduates (RBG). This includes information about the Dr. Leonard F. Sain Award, the Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. scholarship and symposium, the Camp Michigania retreat, and annual reunion for black graduates photographs, planning materials, and souvenir books.
African Americans -- Education (Higher) -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Michigan alumnus.; Minorities -- Education (Higher) -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation, Female.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Michigan.; Audio cassettes.; Digital file formats.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.; University of Michigan. African American Alumni Council.; University of Michigan. Alumnae Council.; University of Michigan -- Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan -- Alumni and alumnae -- Anniversaries, etc.; Alumni Memorial Hall (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan Black Alumni.; University of Michigan -- Commencements.; University of Michigan. Center for Continuing Education of Women.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan. Martin Luther King, Jr. Symposium Committee.; University of Michigan. Medical Alumni Association.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. Reunion of Black Alumni.; University of Michigan. Society of Alumni.; Angus, David L.; Collins, Francis S.; Burton Tower (University of Michigan); Henderson House (University of Michigan); Jenson, Jens, 1860-1951.; Marzolf, Marion.; Michigan League.; Michigan State University.; Morgan, Robert O.; Oksenberg, Michel, 1938-; Prentiss, James Henry, 1872-1960.; Shaw, Wilfred Byron, 1881-1959.; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Tapping, Theodore Hawley, 1889-1969.; Werling, Donn Paul.; Williams Professorship Fund (University of Michigan)
- Administrative Files, 1897-1999; undated
  Administrative Files (boxes 1-53; 55-67; 124-125; 131; 157; and 168) includes correspondence (boxes 1-67; and 168) spans the period from 1897-1999 when the various alumni and professional societies were combined into the Alumni Association. The basic arrangement of the correspondence is in chronological periods and thereunder in a basic alphabetical sequence. The bulk of the correspondence is that of the Alumni Association General Secretary (later Executive Director) although correspondence of field secretaries and other alumni officers is also present. Subject access to the correspondence is largely non-existent. In order to make use of these records some familiarity with key individuals or events in the history of the university is required. Much of the correspondence is routine in nature, pertaining to more mundane matters like payment of dues, subscriptions to the Michigan Alumnus and requests for football tickets. Interspersed among the mundane letters, however, are news items and reminiscences from alumni, information on various class memorials and responses to various Alumni Association requests such as names of alumni who fought in the Civil War, Spanish American War and later wars. Information on films and recordings detailing the work of the university which were made available to alumni groups is also interspersed among the correspondence.
  Of particular note is correspondence surrounding the building of Alumni Memorial Hall (now the Art Museum). Built during 1908-1910, the planning, design, and intended use of the building was frequently discussed during the years from 1903 to 1912. Much of this discussion and fundraising took place at the same time a similar campaign was underway for the Michigan Union. Conflict between the two proposals as well as confusion among alumni solicited for funds by both campaigns is evident in the correspondence covering this period. Issues of the Michigan Alumnus during this period also help to frame the issues surrounding this controversy. Additional documentation on building projects is available in the Special Projects and Subjects series. Other key eras such as World War II are reflected in extensive correspondence with alumni in the armed services. Other materials within this series include alumni directories (including Black, Hispanic, Mexican, and Puerto Rican alumni), a list of directors and officers of the Alumni Association, meeting minutes, and retreat documemtation.
  - Correspondence, 1897-1993
    - 1897-1904 (Box 1)
    - 1905-1906 (Box 2)
    - 1907-April 1908 (Box 3)
    - May 1908-December 1909 (Box 4)
    - 1910-July 1911 (Box 5)
      - [A-S] (Box 5)
      - [T-Z] (Box 6)
    - 1911-1915 (Box 6)
    - June 1916-June 1922
      - [A-B] (Box 6)
      - [C-H] (Box 7)
      - [I-R] (Box 8)
      - [S-Z] (Box 9)
    - 1922-1927 (Box 10)
    - 1928-1929
      - [A-N] (Box 10)
      - [O-Z] (Box 11)
    - 1930-1931
      - [A-D] (Box 11)
      - [E-T] (Box 12)
      - [U-Z] (Box 13)
    - 1932-1933
      - [A-S] (Box 13)
      - [T-Z] (Box 14)
    - 1934-1935
      - [A-G] (Box 14)
      - [H-Z] (Box 15)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 16)
      - [A-D] (Box 16)
      - [E-O] (Box 17)
      - [P-Z] (Box 18)
    - 1938-1939
      - [A] (Box 18)
      - [B-G] (Box 19)
      - [H-T] (Box 20)
      - [U-Z] (Box 21)
    - 1940-1941
      - [A-B] (Box 21)
    - 1940-1941
      - [C-M] (Box 22)
      - [M-T] (Box 23)
      - [U-Z] (Box 24)
    - 1942-1943
      - [A-B] (Box 24)
      - [C-J] (Box 25)
      - [K-R] (Box 26)
      - [S-Z] (Box 27)
    - 1944-1945
      - [A] (Box 27)
      - [B-G] (Box 28)
      - [H-R] (Box 29)
      - [S-Z] (Box 30)
    - 1945-1946
      - [A-F] (Box 30)
      - [G-V] (Box 31)
      - [W-Z] (Box 32)
    - 1946-1947
      - [A-R] (Box 32)
      - [S-Z] (Box 33)
    - 1947-1948
      - [A-D] (Box 33)
      - [E-S] (Box 34)
      - [T-Z] (Box 35)
    - 1948-1949
      - [A-L] (Box 35)
      - [M-Z] (Box 36)
    - 1949-1950
      - [A] (Box 36)
      - [B-K] (Box 37)
    - [L-Ri] (no Rh-Z) (Box 38)
    - 1950-1951
      - [A-I] (Box 39)
      - [J-S] (Box 40)
      - [T-Z] (Box 41)
    - 1951-1952
      - [A-B] (Box 41)
      - [C-O] (Box 42)
      - [P-Z] (Box 43)
    - 1952-1953
      - [A-B] (Box 43)
      - [B-L] (Box 44)
      - [L-W] (Box 45)
    - 1953-1954
      - [A-K] (Box 46)
      - [L-Z] (Box 47)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 48)
      - [A-D] (Box 48)
      - [F-T] (no E) (Box 49)
      - [U-W] (no XYZ) (Box 50)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 51)
      - [A-F] (Box 51)
      - [G-S] (Box 52)
      - [T-Z] (Box 53)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 53)
      (A-Z)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 55)
      (unorganized)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 56)
    - 1999 (Box 168)
    - Field Secretary, 1946-1950 (Box 57)
    - R.O. Morgan, 1938-1957
      - 1938-1954
        - A-C (Box 58)
        - D-H (Box 59)
        - I-M (Box 60)
        - N-R (Box 61)
        - S-U (Box 62)
        - V-Z (Box 63)
      - 1954-1957
        - A-F (Box 63)
        - G-Z (Box 64)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1936-1950 (Box 65)
    - Harold Wilson Correspondence, 1951-1956 (Box 66)
    - Harold Wilson Correspondence, 1951-1956 (Box 67)
      (continued)
    - Topical File of T. Hawley Tapping, 1945-1949
      - A-? (Box 124)
      - ?-Z (Box 125)
  - Directories, 1991-1994; undated
    - Black and Hispanic alumni, undated (Box 168)
    - Hispanic, Mexican, and Puerto Rican American alumni, 1994 (Box 168)
    - Native American alumni, 1994 (Box 168)
    - Staff Listings, 1991 (Box 168)
  - Directors and Officers of Alumni Association, 1897-1967 (Box 157)
  - General (includes purpose), 1963-1987 (Box 157)
  - Minutes and Reports, 1939-1999
    (occasionally includes Alumnae Council)
    - 1939 (Box 131)
    - 1940 (Box 131)
    - 1941 (Box 131)
    - 1942 (Box 131)
    - 1943 (Box 131)
    - 1944 (Box 131)
    - 1945 (Box 131)
    - 1946 (Box 131)
    - 1947 (Box 131)
    - 1948 (Box 131)
    - 1949 (Box 131)
    - 1950 (Box 131)
    - 1951 (Box 131)
    - 1952 (Box 131)
    - 1953 (Box 131)
    - 1954 (Box 131)
    - 1955 (Box 131)
    - 1956-1967, 1978-1979; 8 folders (Box 131)
    - 1992-1999 (with gaps) (Box 168)
  - Retreat, 1984 (Box 157)
- Alumnae Council Files, 1921-1998
  Alumnae Council Files (Boxes 114-117, 131-133) include general material on the council which was formed to keep up to date with the needs and life of women at the University of Michigan and to report those activities to alumnae. Records reflect the early distinction made between alumni and alumnae and detail the operation of the council and efforts to aid women students with financial needs as well as the operation of the Michigan League. (See also the Michigan League Building Fund Campaign Files in boxes 105-108, the 1924 Alumnae Council Survey Questionnaire in boxes 109-110, and the Alumnae Club File in boxes 111-113). Information on Henderson House, a women's cooperative dormitory sponsored by the Alumnae Council is also present. Later records reflect efforts to integrate the separate alumnae activities into the larger operation of the Alumni Association. Of particular note are several files relating to women students and alumnae involved in World War II military service and war work (located in boxes 114-115). These files include accounts of military service, articles about work in locations such as the Willow Run Bomber Plant, and photographs of alumnae in service (WACS, WAVES, Red Cross). An index card file compiles information on alumnae involved in military service.
  Related to the Alumnae Council files are the Marjorie Williams Papers (.5 linear feet; 1958-1962) which consist of administrative records pertaining to the work of the Alumnae Council during the latter part of the 1950s and the early 1960s. The folders are arranged alphabetically by topic with the items in each folder arranged chronologically. The majority of the records are minutes and reports of workshops, functions and special committees of the council. The largest folder, "Correspondence", contains letters to and from the Alumni Association and the Alumnae Secretary, Allison Myers, as well as other groups and organizations. The letters give information about the day-to-day workings of the organization not seen in the minutes and reports. Of interest is the folder containing information on the Alice Freeman Palmer Professor Committee. Dr. George H. Palmer gave an endowment to the Alumnae Council to establish a chair in the history department in the name of his wife. The full time position was approved in 1958, with Dr. Sylvia L. Thrupp as the first appointee. The folder contains a newsletter about Dr. Thrupp and the endowment.
  Connected with the work of the Alumnae Council is the 1924 Alumnae Council Survey Questionnaire. As part of the effort to establish the Michigan League surveys were sent to every woman that had attended the university up to 1924. The survey questionnaires asked for biographical information as well as occupations, leadership positions, and queried alumnae to consider who were the ten most influential alumnae. Returned questionnaires are located in boxes 109-110. An index, including cross references to maiden names is contained in a separate volume. Additional biographical and genealogical information on alumnae is available in the separate University of Michigan. Alumni Records. Necrology File record group. This record groups includes an extensive name index of former students and graduates.
  A similar alumni survey was contemplated in 1927. The 1927 Alumni Survey (located in Box 130) contains the partial results of this effort to contact every graduate and former student that had attended the university. To test the feasibility of such a vast undertaking surveys were sent to all alumni with surnames beginning with the letters "A" and "B." Approximately 60% of the surveys were completed and returned. Realizing how costly it would be to complete the rest of the survey, the undertaking was abandoned. Among the biographical information asked in the survey was occupation, activities, community work, and sources of income. An index to the extant surveys is contained in a separate volume along with the 1924 alumnae survey index. Additional biographical and genealogical information on alumni is available in the separate University of Michigan. Alumni Records. Necrology File record group. This record groups includes an extensive name index of former students and graduates.
  - Alumnae Club File, 1931-1956
    - Akron, Ohio (Box 111)
    - Ann Arbor (Box 111)
    - Battle Creek (Box 111)
    - Bay City (Box 111)
    - Benton Harbor (Box 111)
    - Birmingham (Box 111)
    - Buffalo, New York (Box 111)
    - Chicago, Illinois (Box 111)
    - Cleveland, Ohio (Box 111)
    - Columbus, Ohio (Box 111)
    - Detroit (Box 111)
    - Flint (Box 111)
    - Ft. Wayne, Indiana (Box 112)
    - Grand Rapids (Box 112)
    - Jackson (Box 112)
    - Kalamazoo (Box 112)
    - Lansing (Box 112)
    - Los Angeles, California (Box 112)
    - Marshall (Box 112)
    - Monroe (Box 112)
    - Muskegon (Box 112)
    - New York, New York (Box 112)
    - Owosso (Box 112)
    - Philadelphia, Pennsylvania (Box 113)
    - Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania (Box 113)
    - Pontiac (Box 113)
    - Royal Oak (Box 113)
    - Saginaw (Box 113)
    - St. Louis, Missouri (Box 113)
    - San Francisco (Box 113)
    - Seattle, Washington (Box 113)
    - South Bend, Indiana (Box 113)